<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Now and ever; shewing, where the work of conversion is thoroughly done, it is done for ever. / By William Jemmat, preacher of the Gospel in Reading.</title>
            <author>Jemmat, William, 1596?-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J550A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617612</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617612</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2725:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Now and ever; shewing, where the work of conversion is thoroughly done, it is done for ever. / By William Jemmat, preacher of the Gospel in Reading.</title>
                  <author>Jemmat, William, 1596?-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Miller for John Chandler, bookseller in Reading,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two leaves contain titlepage (reverse blank) and preface to the reader, signed W.J.</note>
                  <note>Sermon based on Isaiah, chapter 40, verses 30-31.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XL, 30-31 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175268:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175268:1"/>
            <p>NOW and EVER; SHEWING, Where the Work of Converſion is throughly done, it is done for ever.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESA. 46.3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hearken unto me, O houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all the remnant of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are born by me from the belly, which are carryed from the womb. And even to your old age I am he, and even to hoar haires will I car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry you: I have made, and I will bear, even I will carry and will deliver you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 48.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This God is our God for ever and ever; he will be our guide even unto death.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>William Jemmat,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Miller</hi> for <hi>John Chandler,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Reading.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175268:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175268:2"/>
            <head>To the Serious Reader.</head>
            <p>THere be two weighty truths about the grace of Converſion in a ſoul that ſhall be ſaved: One, that of neceſſity it muſt be done in this preſent life, according to that of <hi>Salomon,</hi> Eccl. <hi>9.10. Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might: for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave whither thou goeſt.</hi> Now or Never. The other, that when this work is once done well, in ſome good manner as it ought to be done, it is done for ever, and ſhall never fail the Chriſtian here or hereafter. The former is a matter of ſerious diligence and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: The latter, of ſtrong and full conſolation. Happy is the ſoul that ſuffers it ſelf to be perſwaded and over-ruled in preſent, to do this great buſineſs of coming home to his God, and joyning it ſelf to him in a perpetual Covenant that ſhall never be forgotten. Hereby it hath done a work which ſhall laſt to Eternity, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ver be undone any more. <hi>Now and Ever.</hi> And it is ſuch a work, as ſhall ſtand it in ſtead whatever ſad occaſions ſhall meet it in this evil and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome world. Believers amidſt all bodily infirmities, and temptations, and afflictions of this life, yet in their God to whom through rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they are come at converſion, have a ſure and ſtrong ſtay to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and may ſay as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. <hi>73.26. My fleſh and my heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever.</hi> O precious portion for a ſoul to find ſetling and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! A portion is that wich falls to a man upon diviſion of Land or Goods. Now the Lord in his moſt wiſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>spenſation allots to ſome a portion in temporals: <hi>They have their portion in this life,</hi> Pſal. <hi>17.14.</hi> To others he reſerves himſelf for a portion, who is infinitely better then the multitude of Riches, Pleaſures, Honours, and all the fineſt accommodations. And becauſe God is the portion of Believers, therefore it is <hi>the good part, or portion,</hi> Luke <hi>10.42.</hi> It is a blisfull portion, and makes thoſe for ever happy who ſhare in it, <hi>Pſal.
<pb facs="tcp:175268:3"/>
144.15.</hi> It is an all-ſufficient portion, and in every respect able to ſerve our turns, and give complete contentment, <hi>Gen. 17.1.</hi> And it is an everlaſting portion: <hi>my portion for ever,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us the Lord becomes the portion of a believing ſoul, partly by his own free and voluntary giving himſelf to it, both in his eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and purpoſe, as alſo by actual application; partly by the ſouls vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary accepting, owning, and chuſing the Lord for a portion, with which it will reſt ſatisfied, Lam. <hi>3.24. The Lord is my portion,</hi> ſaith my ſoul. The Lord himſelf perſwade, ſtrengthen, and eſtabliſh our hearts by believing, that we may reſt contented with this our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be in ſome meaſure thankful for it: that ſeeing he hath vouchſafed to be our portion, we may ever think it fitting and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be a peculiar people and portion unto him, Deut. <hi>32 9. The Lords portion is his people,</hi> Jacob <hi>is the lot of his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175268:3"/>
            <head>Now and Ever.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH 40.30, 31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even the youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the young men ſhall utterly fall.</p>
                  <p>But they that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength; they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the beginning of this Chapter the Lord by his Prophet had promiſed great and glorious things to his poor Church, as return out of the Babyloniſh Captivity, with wonderful mercies procuring and accompanying the ſame, and ſuch as reach to the times of the Goſpel, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Chriſt comes to do it, and the Baptiſt makes way for him; therefore Believers may expect performance: Which that they may do, the Prophet doth lively ſet forth the Power and Wiſdom of God, which are the main helps to accompliſh his Decrees: he knows how to do it, and he is able to do it: and a Believer may eaſily collect, that if the Lord be ſo powerful and careful in the Government of the world, how much more will he ſo be for the good of his Church and Choſen?</p>
            <p>Then it might be objected, Yea but the Church ſeems to be of all other moſt neglected, and is moſt troubled in the world; and this makes us even <hi>faint,</hi> and caſt hope away, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. For this they are blamed in the Verſes following, and told, that God is ſufficient for his Church againſt all her enemies, and in all her faintneſs; and they ſhall ſee Great Ones of the world fail and come to nothing, when his people ſhall ſurvive and be triumphant.</p>
            <p>This laſt is the mind of the Holy Ghoſt in theſe two laſt Verſes, which have an amplification of the Churches ſtrength
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175268:4"/>
by oppoſition to the ſtrength of nature, and of the world: <hi>Even the youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the young men ſhall ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly fall: but they that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength; they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint:</hi> As if he had ſaid, None have the ſtrength that Gods people have, no not the ſtouteſt and choyceſt men that are, whom Generals and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of War do pick out from the reſt, and moſt truſt in, and brag of their puiſſance; yet faintneſs comes upon ſuch by Hunger, Cold, Watching, Travelling, Fighting, rumors that they hear of the enemies might, fear which the Lord ſends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſpirits a thouſand wayes to cool their courage. But my people go upon better and higher Principles, namely of my favour, and of my ſpecial grace in them, whereby through believing they ſhall become ſtrong out of weakneſs, and hold out to a full and glorious victory over all enemies, both from hell and in the world.</p>
            <p>Now this oppoſition of ſtrength and ſtrength leads us to theſe two Propoſitions: One, That all created ſtrength is of a fainting and failing nature. The other, That the ſtrength whereby true Chriſtians ſtand in the favour of God, and the expectation of heaven, is greater and better then all the ſtrength of nature, even taken at the beſt and ſtrongeſt.</p>
            <p>Briefly of the former: All created ſtrength is of a fainting and failing nature. Though there be not only a firm and healthy body, but much courage of mind, with aſſiſtance of Arts and Parts, and alliance of Friends, and all encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are to be had, yet in the Event all prevailes not to attain the deſired end. <hi>Even the youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the young men ſhall utterly fall. The race is not to the ſwift, nor the battel to the ſtrong, neither yet bread to the wiſe, nor yet riches to men of underſtanding, nor yet favour to men of skill,</hi> Eccl. 9.11. It is true, by thoſe accompliſhments nature may attain to live long in the world, to riſe high in the world, to get a great Eſtate, to have great Victories over enemies, with other great matters which Weaklings may not once think to attain. But beſide the ſad diſappointments which theſe ſometimes meet withall, even amidſt all their bravery they commit foul
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175268:4"/>
errours, they ſhorten their dayes by Intemperance, they fall into Conſumptions, or at beſt, the longer they live, the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer they draw to their end: and it is ſeen ordinarily, that the Bell rings out, and the Grave opens for young ones as well as for the old; few now-a-days come to the Age ſet in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, of threeſcore and ten, or fourſcore.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is, by the fall ſin hath diſabled our nature, both in powers of the body and mind, and ſo miniſters occaſion to the great God of heaven to cut us ſhort of our hope and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities: <hi>Our ſins withhold good things from us, Jer.</hi> 5.25. And, the Lord will have the fineſt Naturaliſts ſee, that not by might or power, but by his ſpirit great things are to be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>He takes the wiſe in their craftineſs, he turns their counſel into fooliſhneſs; he ſhews ſtrength with his arm, he ſcatters the proud in the imagination of their hearts; he puts down the mighty from their ſeats, and exalteth men of low degree; he filleth the hungry with good things, and the rich he ſends empty away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Application make thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. See what a poor happineſs the happineſs of worldlings is. When they are at their height, and in the beſt eſtate they can be in here below, or deſire to be in (with a real and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar deſire) ſo that their Neighbours take them to be happy creatures, and they think no leſs of themſelves, yet indeed they fall much ſhort of the true happineſs; and godly men ſhall not change Eſtates with them, though poor and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as to the world. Why? becauſe the beſt and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete attainments they have, are but fading Commodities: the one ſtroke of Death cuts the thred of their whole happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; there comes a Fever or other miſchievous Diſeaſe, and ſo an end of the man and all his braveries: So that neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath cauſe to vaunt, or pleaſe himſelf in his fine conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor others to envy his proſperity while it holds moſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. It is but as the green Bay-tree, flouriſhing in preſent, but ſoon blaſted or cut down, and the place of it ſhall know it no more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let godly Chriſtians bleſs the Lord, who hath laid their happineſs in things of another nature and endurance; namely ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus: that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175268:5"/>
though they be poor, or weak, or otherwiſe low in the world, yet in the beſt matters, through rich mercy, they are highly exalted; none ſo happy as they, indeed none but they. Therefore, not only be contented with your ſhort pittance, but thankful that your lines are fallen unto you <hi>in pleaſant pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and ye have a <hi>goodly heritage, Pſal.</hi> 16.6. Had your lot fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len otherwiſe to you, you had been of all men moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Think of <hi>Dives</hi> tormented in thoſe flames, and of the rich Churl whoſe ſoul in a night was taken from him, and ſo an end of all his plenty and jollity. Think how <hi>David</hi> bleſſed himſelf from faring as worldly-minded men ſhall fare: <hi>Let me not eat of their dainties, Pſal.</hi> 141.4. and again, <hi>Deliver my ſoul from the wicked, from men which are thy hand, O Lord, from men of the world who have their portion in this life, and whoſe belly thou filleſt with thy hid treaſure: they are full of Children, and leave the reſt of their ſubſtance to their Babes.</hi> Then refer all to the happineſs that ſhall be revealed at the laſt day, as the Prophet there concludes, <hi>As for me, I will behold thy face in righteouſneſs, I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs,</hi> Pſal. 17.14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If all preſent comforts be ſo weak and fickle, <hi>Let not the ſtrong man glory in his ſtrength, nor the rich man in his riches, nor the wiſe man in his wiſdom,</hi> Jer. 9.23. Fine accommodations theſe are, and conduce much to make ones life comfortable; and he that is a wiſe Maſter of them, may do much good in his place and Generation, and greatly further his accounts in the day of accounting with God: But alaſs! they are but moth-eaten and poor comforts in themſelves, very like to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs</hi> Gourd which came up in a night, and periſhed in a night. When we think we have them ſafeſt, and take moſt pleaſure in them, they dye in our hands as flowers which we gathered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rewhile, and we our ſelves paſs away with them, we know not how ſoon: And the wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not? for riches certainly make themſelves wings: they fly away as an Eagle toward heaven, Prov.</hi> 23.5. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid by the wiſdom given unto him, <hi>Rejoyce as not rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> and in all your enjoyments be <hi>as if ye had them not,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.30. Remember, Chriſtians, and not over-joy in a luſty Child,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175268:5"/>
a ſetled eſtate of health, tallneſs, comelineſs, or properneſs of the body, the increaſe of a wealthy eſtate, a great inheritance either by deſcent or purchaſe. There is death in the pot; a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret worm lies at the root, and bites ſhrewdly: and all the joy may quickly be mar'd: and then, the more joy was, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will be the grief at parting, and ſhame for the former boaſting, to ſee things turned to the quite con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If natural comforts be turned upon ſuch a wheel, then truſt not in an arm fleſh: <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſon of man in whom there is no help: His breath goeth forth, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth to his earth, in that day all his thoughts periſh,</hi> Pſal. 146.3, 4. Nor may Princes truſt in mighty and puiſſant armies, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, warlike proviſions, multitude of an hoſte, or the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel they can take; all theſe have failed ſome that relied on them, and may fail others who reſt on them as able to ſave. Nor may we reſt upon potent friends, who are able to do much themſelves, and uſe their intereſt in others for raiſing a party. Nor upon health and ſtrength of body, nimbleneſs, or other natural perfections. Nor upon a ſtrong wit, a deep reach, a firm and retentive memory, eloquence in diſcourſing, fitneſs of expreſſions, with other gifts of the mind: All com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a ſtaff of reed, whereon if a man lean, he may get a fall, it may be periſh by the ſplinters running into his hand. Certainly this truſting in creatures, hinders faith in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and brings a curſe in ſtead of a bleſſing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Curſed be the man that trusteth in man, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord;</hi> and ver. 7. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is.</hi> Take heed, Chriſtians, and <hi>beware of the evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God, Heb.</hi> 3.12. which in this our corrupt nature theſe Puppets are apt to do.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>leneſs of nature and natural things yieldeth ſundry good inſtructions to young people, and to the Parents.</p>
            <p>Parents briefly are admoniſhed in three things. Firſt, not to pride themſelves in luſty and likely Children, as too many uſe to do, making them ſo many idols, and promiſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great comfort by them; it may be, inſulting over other men whoſe Children are weak and ſickly; wherewith the Lord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175268:6"/>
is offended; and ſometime the likely Children are taken away, or prove croſſes, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weaklings ſurvive, and become comforts to their parents. Secondly parents even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning ſhould commend their children to the Lord by hearty prayer, that if they dye in the birth, or in their youth, yet by Jeſus Chriſt it may be well with their poor ſouls to eternity. <hi>Oh that</hi> Iſmael <hi>might l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve in thy ſight!</hi> Thirdly, they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with them betimes, that by their gracious inſtructions they may quickly come to know and fear the Lord their God, and ſo, whatever becomes of them in the world, yet their poor ſouls may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: the higheſt acts of charity that can be ſhewed to our children.</p>
            <p>Next for young people;</p>
            <p n="1">1. They learn to walk in all humbleneſs of mind, as thoſe that may be ſoon ſnatched away, and while they continue here, are ſubject to many faintings and failings. It concerns all to be cloathed with humility, but eſpecially young people whoſe judgment is not yet ſetled, and they want the experience which in time they may have, neither are they acquainted with themſelves and their manifold weakneſſes as in time they may be, ſo that it is neither ſafe nor ſeemly for ſuch to be ſhewing their opinion in matters, to be talking much in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Elder people, eſpecially to take upon them (without a Calling) to teach others, as ſome bold men in theſe days have dangerouſly adventured. Conſider and fear: if ye have the grace of God in you of a truth, yet ye ought to <hi>walk in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſo to be <hi>worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, Eph.</hi> 4.12 Much more, if the work of grace be not yet begun, or not well evidenced: here come thoſe rules to be obſerved, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>Lean not to thine own underſtanding, be not wiſe in thine own eyes, fear the Lord and depart from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Beware of looſe and Libertine courſes, which moſt young people do chuſe, and delight to take, as beſt agreeing with their wild and fooliſh humors: therefore called the luſts of youth, and muſt be carefully <hi>avoided,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 22. <hi>Fly youthful luſts:</hi> As fleſhly luſts, and worldly luſts, and luſts of the mind, ſo the luſts of youth, which are either peculiar to young peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or moſt affected. Remember, and conſider how theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175268:6"/>
luſts are apt to foreſtall all good inſtructions of the word, that there is no room for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>her they cannot enter, or if they do, they are ſoon thruſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gain, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.19. <hi>The luſts of other things entring choak the word,</hi> and it becometh unfruitful. When our young people are nipt in the bud, they are ſcarce good ever afterward. Our looſe times have ſhewed it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. And after ſuch lawleſneſs of young people comes that fearful ſummons, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Rejoyce O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thy eyes: but know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee unto judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing all within you and without you is ſo fading and uncertain, lift up your eyes and hearts to the Creator, to get in with him, and by him to obtain a ſolid and laſting good, which may be ſufficient for you in all other faintings and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth,</hi> and (which is the <hi>whole duty of man) fear God and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Eccl.</hi> 12.1, 13. The wiſe man there had reckoned up all the vanities of the world, and preſcribed remedies againſt them; and then bids us <hi>hear the concluſion of the whole matter,</hi> in thoſe two precepts. When the ſoul is tyred out with the conſideration of earthly vanities and diſtractive occurrences, it ſhould be think it ſelf of getting home to his Ark where it may find reſt for the ſoal of his foot, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7. <hi>Return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy reſt, O my ſoul: for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.</hi> It ſhould be good inſtruction both to young and old, when they find themſelves perplexed or pricked with thorns of the world (as who of us doth not?) to return to our God, from whom by ſin we departed. Never till then ſhall we find reſt and aſſured confidence, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2 6, 7. When the Lord <hi>hedged</hi> up the Churches way with thorns, that ſhe could <hi>not find her paths,</hi> then ſhe ſaid, <hi>I will go and return to my firſt husband, for then was it better with me, then now.</hi> And if young people in their young days would bethink themſelves of returning to the Lord their God, they might ſave themſelves many ſcrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and woundings which afterward they are put to endure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Seeing all theſe things are ſo, ye ſhould all receive the exhortation which we give ſo often, Make ſure of Chriſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175268:7"/>
Make ſure of Chriſt; in him alone ye can find reſt for your ſouls, there is no ſalvation in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er, no Name elſe given under heaven by which y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n be ſaved; not Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor any of the creatures, nor all of them put together; all together could not redeem one ſoul, nor make up the peace with the great God. But in and by Chriſt all is firm and ſtable; everlaſting love, everlaſting compaſſions, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arms to embrace the Penitent; an everlaſting covenant promiſes moſt certain, and ſure to be performed, <hi>Yea and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. Bear us witneſs, Chriſtians, we invite you day by day to come and receive Chriſt for your own; we urge you with many Motives; we tell you of your ſin and danger; and in the mean time ye feel in your ſelves the decays of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſee in the mortality of your Neighbours, what your caſe muſt be, and ye know not how ſoon. Once at laſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be wiſe, and <hi>Kiſs the Son of God,</hi> that in the worſt ſtraights ye may find enlargement, and be <hi>bleſſed, Pſal.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Bleſſed are they that truſt in him.</hi> If ye were commanded to do ſome great thing for bleſſedneſs, would ye not do it? how much more when he ſaith, <hi>Believe and ye ſhall be ſaved;</hi> and, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him, ſhall not be confounded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the other Propoſition;</p>
            <p>The ſtrength whereby true Chriſtians ſtand in the favor of God, and the expectation of heaven, is greater and better then all the ſtrength of nature, even taken at the beſt and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. When the likelieſt <hi>faint and are weary,</hi> yet they ſhall <hi>renew their ſtrength, mount up with wings, run and not be weary, walk and not faint:</hi> Where we have, both a plain affirmation, of <hi>renewing their ſtrength,</hi> and a borrowed ſpeech, of <hi>Eagles</hi> who caſt their Bill when they be old, and ſo get to be lively again; when their crooked Bill is put away, they take in their meat as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and grow as ſtrong as ever. All noting the perpetuity of the eſtate of grace, wherein when the Elect fail at any time, through mercy they recover all, and hold out to the end of their courſe; <hi>They are strong in the Lord, and the power of his might.</hi> On him they wait in the uſe of means, and of him the receive ſtrength a new to be conſtant. <hi>He ſtrengthneth they with ſtrength in their ſoul, Pſal.</hi> 138.3. Amidſt many occaſiom
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175268:7"/>
of fainting, their inward man is <hi>renewed day by day,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. They call in freſh ſupplies by <hi>prayer,</hi> and ſo are <hi>ſtrengthned with might by the Spirit in the inner man, Eph.</hi> 3.16. And the prayer of other Believers ſends in thoſe freſh ſupplies, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.11. <hi>That ye may be ſtrengthned with all might according to his glorious power, unto all patience and long-ſuffering with joyfulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certain it is, that the Lord hath undertaken to be the ſtrength of his people: <hi>The rock of their ſalvation, the ſtrength of their ſalvation, the horn of ſalvation</hi> which he raiſed up in the houſe of his ſervant <hi>David;</hi> and as much as the Creator is mighty above the creatures, ſo is a godly man above himſelf and all his natural abilities. In and of God he receives ſuch puiſſant vertue, and ſo may grow confident, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.4. <hi>Truſt ye in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord</hi> Jehova <hi>is everlaſting ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpecial, Chriſt himſelf is the ſtrength of his choſen ones. He gives them his fleſh which is meat indeed, and his bloud which is drink indeed. He makes then a banquet at his own coſt, and with his own merits, to feed them unto eternal life: that though the old <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſs did eat Manna and dye after it, yet ſo ſhall not they.</p>
            <p>And as his merit is ſo efficacious, ſo his Spirit abides with them for ever; guides, leads into all truth, brings all things to their remembrance, and eſtabliſheth their hearts in this their gracious, and bleſſed eſtate. There is a vertue in his death, that they can dye no more in their ſins: and a vertue in his reſurrection, which makes them living members of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and living branches of the true Vine, to draw ſap and juice from him, and be ſtill pruned that they may bear more fruit.</p>
            <p>Further proofs of this unvanquiſhable ſtrength of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
            <p>One Scripture ſaith of the godly, <hi>The righteous is an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foundation, Prov.</hi> 10.25. He in Scripture is called <hi>righteous,</hi> who is juſtified and ſanctified: and he is called a <hi>foundation,</hi> to note his firm and ſtable condition; and, as a foundation, he <hi>bears up the pilla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth,</hi> both Church and State.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture ſaith, God who hath begun a good work
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175268:8"/>
in his people, will finiſh or perform it untill the day of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6. When the work of converſion unto God is once well done, it is done for ever; it is (as he ſaid of his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an everlaſting poſſeſſion: for God who is the Alpha, is alſo the Omega.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture ſaith, Chriſt having loved his own which were in the world, <hi>did love them unto the end, John</hi> 13.1 and he ſaith himſelf, chap. 10.28. <hi>I give unto my ſheep eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any man pluck them out of my hand;</hi> no nor Devil; but in him that loved them, they are more then Conquerors.</p>
            <p>Other Scriptures ſound forth priviledges: <hi>The righteous ſhall hold on his way; and he that hath clean hands, ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger,</hi> Job 17.9. <hi>They that are planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God, and ſtill bring forth fruit in old age,</hi> Pſal. 92.14. <hi>They that truſt in the Lord, ſhall be as mount Sion, which cannot be removed, but abideth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 125.1. The fear of the Lord is ſo put into their hearts, that they <hi>ſhall not depart from him, Jer.</hi> 32.40. Their houſe is built upon a rock, ſo as <hi>it ſhall not fall,</hi> though the winds blow ſtrong, and the waters flow a main, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.25. with other firm and undeniable grounds of perſevering in grace, which follow afterward: all proving, that true Believers ſhall ſtill <hi>renew their ſtrength, and not faint nor be weary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it may be asked, How doth the Lord renew ſtrength to his people? The anſwer is, He renews their ſtrength in the uſe of holy means appointed thereunto; namely thoſe ſacred Ordinances which he hath ſet apart, firſt and laſt to carry on the work of grace in the hearts of his Choſen: which that they may indeed obtain, he puts them into a frame of <hi>waiting</hi> on his Majeſty in his own way, wherein he will meet them, and beſtow a bleſſing on them, as he hath promiſed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Now he that hath wrought us for the ſelf ſame end thing, is God, who alſo hath given unto us the earneſt of the Spirit.</hi> So at the Text, it ſtands as a Deſcription of the godly, They are ſuch as <hi>wait upon the Lord;</hi> they muſt know they are Servants, and need dependance on the heavenly Maſter, and as Servants muſt <hi>wait</hi> till they receive mercy at his hands: and ſo they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175268:8"/>
ſhall be ſure to ſpeed of their ſuit. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25. <hi>The Lord is good unto them that wait for him, to the ſoul that ſeeketh him.</hi> A Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces good Servant ever ſtands in the way of preferment: and ſo for Chriſtianity. To ſpeed of ſtrength and every comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſupply, we muſt be careful to be found in the way of faith and obedience.</p>
            <p>Here note theſe phraſes of Scripture;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wait at the Poſts of his doors, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that heareth me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt the wiſdom of God, <hi>watching daily at my gates, waiting at the poſts of my doors.</hi> Thriving Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt diligently attend when a good Sermon is to be heard, or a Sacrament to be received, or a Faſt to be kept, or elſe a day of Thankſgiving. They muſt come both prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly and forwardly: neither be abſent, nor yet backward, but come upon the wing <hi>as Doves to their houſes when purſued by a bird of prey,</hi> Eſa. 60.8. <hi>ſwift to hear,</hi> Jam. 1.19. <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Company, when <hi>Peter</hi> was coming to preach, were ready beforehand to hear what he ſhould ſay, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.33. <hi>We are all here preſent before God, to hear all things that are commanded thee of God,</hi> with ver. 24. <hi>Cornelius waited for them,</hi> and had called together his Kinſmen and near friends. And it is a great ſin in many, to make the Miniſter and Congregation <hi>wait</hi> when they will pleaſe to appear.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wait till he have mercy, Pſal.</hi> 123.2. Behold, as the eyes of Servants look unto the hand of their Maſters, and as the eyes of a Maiden to the hand of her Miſtreſs, ſo <hi>our eyes wait upon the Lord our God, untill that he have mercy upon us.</hi> He hath promiſed great things to his people: but his people muſt <hi>wait</hi> for performance. The Viſion of comfort will <hi>speak</hi> at laſt, and <hi>not deceive;</hi> but in the mean time we muſt <hi>wait</hi> to ſee when God will pleaſe to anſwer our expectation, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And he that believeth muſt not make haſte,</hi> ſo limiting the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> much leſs rage or murmure, or be impotent of mind; leaſt of all to utter that blaſpheming voice, <hi>This evil is of the Load, and ſhall I wait for the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.33. Remember, it is a mercy to ſpeed at the laſt; if ever we be heard in prayer, it is enough: enough if ever an <hi>Iſaac</hi> be had, or ſupply, or comfort, or deliverance. This that I ſaid,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175268:9"/>
               <hi>We muſt wait in the way of faith:</hi> not only to the ſecond and third watch of the night, but till morning. <hi>Davids ſoul waited for the Lord, more then they that wait for the morning, yea more then they that wait for the morning,</hi> Pſal. 130.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Wait upon the Office</hi> which God or man hath aſſigned thee unto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7. <hi>If we have received the miniſtery, let us wait on our miniſtring: or he that teacheth, on teaching: or he that exhorteth, on exhortation.</hi> And by the like reaſon, a Magiſtrate muſt <hi>wait on governing,</hi> an Houſholder <hi>on looking to the ways of</hi> his Family, a Servant on doing his buſineſs painfully and faithfully, a Child in his place, a poor creature in humble walking: In every of which while we ſerve our Brethren, or diſpatch our own affairs; yet, doing all as we ought, we ſhall ſerve the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and wait on him <hi>in the way of our obedience:</hi> eſpecially if we make a buſineſs of our Calling, and <hi>abide</hi> upon it, and watch all opportunities for advancing the glory of God, and our own reckoning: not as thoſe that are in and out, when they have hit into a good way, fickle, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, only good by fits and ſtarts, who are not likely to inherit the promiſes; the promiſe is to them that are conſtant, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord: and this is the right <hi>waiting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Wait for the Lord in the way of his judgments,</hi> Eſa. 26.8. <hi>Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O Lord, have we waited for thee;</hi> the deſire of our ſoul is to thy Name, and to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee; namely, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> good uſe of afflictions, and <hi>learn righteouſneſs by them,</hi> as ver. 9. <hi>The Inhabitants of the world will learn righteouſneſs.</hi> The Lord ſometimes corrects his people, it may be with ſore and grievous corrections; yet even then they muſt abide with him, each one according to his Calling, and ſtudy to be better for the ſharp Viſitation, ſaying, What would the Lord have me to do? or wherein may I be better, or do better then I have done? Lord, ſhew me for what thou contendeſt with me: and not only chaſtiſe me thus, but <hi>teach me out of thy law,</hi> that by all thy Diſcipline I may be <hi>bleſſed</hi> at the laſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94 12. It concerns Gods Children to wait on their Father, not only when he cauſeth their way to proſper, that they even waſh their footſteps in butter, but when he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175268:9"/>
changeth his diſpenſations toward them, that all is in clouds and ſtorms, and he ſeems an adverſary to them; for, even then they may be made partakers of his holineſs; and when they are proved and humbled, he means to do them good in their latter end.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Wait all the days of thy appointed time,</hi> as did <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 14.14. <hi>If a man dye, ſhall he live again? all the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</hi> It is a great change when death comes, ſo dye well, is the greateſt work we have to do in the world, and we need to take all our time allotted for our being here, to be fitting our ſelves for that great change. All will prove little enough, when we are entring into that narrow Wicket, ſo to paſs into another world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And wait till Chriſt comes to judgment,</hi> as the good ſervant who watcheth for the return of his Lord, and will be careful to do up all his work before hand. Chriſt comes to judge the quick and dead, of all things done in the body, good and evil, and a ſtrict account muſt be given of all: therefore ſtill <hi>wait,</hi> and make ready thy accounts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And wait till the Bridegroom open the door to the wiſe</hi> Virgins. And to be able to enter, provide Oil for thy Lamp in time, and Oil that will hold till midnight, that thou may not be put to borrow: there will be no borrowing at that time, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.9. The wiſe anſwered the fooliſh, <hi>Not ſo, leſt there be not enough for us and you, but go ye rather to them that ſell, and buy for your ſelves.</hi> Yet ſuch fooliſhneſs reigns in many who profeſs to wait for the coming of Chriſt. A lamp of outward profeſſion they have but not ſufficient Oil to feed their Lamp, and ſo are excluded, and left in the dark. They ſeem good a little in the former part of their life, and then wax r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſs. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the ſpirit, and end in the fleſh, either in reſpect of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Practice, and ſo they loſe all the good they have done, and are found treſpaſſers againſt the truth which they have baſely deſerted.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, who they are that <hi>wait on the Lord.</hi> And theſe are they that renew their ſtrength as the Eagles, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the good way of God to the end; So the concluſion remains firm, The way whereby the ſtrength of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175268:10"/>
is maintained, is their attendance on him in an holy courſe of faith and obedience. They muſt <hi>wait</hi> upon him by faith, expecting the performance of his promiſes: And they muſt <hi>wait</hi> upon him by their obedience, in the uſe of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as good ſervants ought to do: and ſo they ſhall <hi>renew their ſtrength</hi> out of all their faintings.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians complain ſometimes of weakneſs in their faith, dulneſs in prayer, hardneſs of heart, and the like corruptions. They are ready to <hi>faint and be weary</hi> in their holy profeſſion. It grieves them, that they proceed no better then they do. They lack but little ſometimes to caſt up all and make Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. Now let ſuch acknowledge and take notice, where their great ſtrength lieth. Faith and obedience will in time reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all this. Let them believe <hi>above hope,</hi> rather then caſt away their confidence, and let them ſtill attend the good Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, which he hath ſanctified and ſet apart for their confirmation in grace; and in time they ſhall ſee all this evil redreſt; they ſhall meet with a ſtrength they know not whence, but only from God, and this ſhall increaſe grace and comfort in their ſouls, and fortifie them yet more to the day of their Redemption, Eſa. 25.9. <hi>It ſhall be ſaid in that day, Lo, this is our God, we have waited for him, and he will ſave us: this is the Lord, we have waited for him, we will be glad, and rejoyce in his ſalvation;</hi> and chap. 26.8. and 30.18. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Bleſſed is he that waiteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly God will not be wanting to his own wayes, nor fail of his promiſes made to Believers: and where is faith to call for them, they ſhall ſurely be fulfilled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.18. <hi>The needy ſhall not alway be forgotten: the expectation of the poor ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for ever;</hi> and Pſal. 10.17. <hi>Lord, thou haſt heard the deſire of the humble; thou wilt prepare their heart: thou wilt cauſe thine ear to hear.</hi> It is not for his glory, to fail his people; or if he ſhould, their hearts would fail them, they would fall quite away, their ſouls would be loſt, and their holy profeſſion greatly diſparaged</p>
            <p>Here it may be objected, that many who waited upon God ſometime, are grown faint and weary, and have utterly loſt all their ſtrength in the matters of Religion. <hi>Anſw.</hi> No doubt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175268:10"/>
but hypocrites may quite fall away, it may be turn to be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: they never waited on God in the way of faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and therefore might well let fall their hopeful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, and plauſible forms of religiouſneſs, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt, that they were not all of us.</hi> Such are all our Apoſtates, whether they be become Papiſts, or Hereticks, or Mockers of Zeal, or Worldlings, or Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their godly Brethren, or profane in the courſe of their lives.</p>
            <p>But whether may not a true Believer loſe his ſtrength, and <hi>faint, and be weary? Anſw.</hi> Though it be a priviledge of the New Covenant, that the grace of Chriſt in his people ſhall not fail and be extinguiſhed; yet they have no ſuch privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as to flouriſh and remain ſtill in the ſame vigor. Their ſtrength may be weakned, though not annulled. As in Nature a ſtrong man may become weak by a Diſeaſe, or by long faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or, by much travelling, or the like; ſo in matters of grace, a tall and luſty Chriſtian may become weak, even as another who is but a Novice and beginner in the School of Chriſt; I mean for a while, and in ſome particular thing, not wholly, nor to the end. A Brother may <hi>be overtaken in a fault:</hi> and another may be <hi>tempted in like manner, Gal.</hi> 6.1. And he that thinketh he ſtandeth, muſt take heed leſt he fall.</p>
            <p>Now in two reſpects may the ſtrength of a true Chriſtian be much abated: both for his grace, and for his comforts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His graces and gracious behaviour may be much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Epheſus left her firſt love;</hi> that is, the meaſure of love to the Goſpel, which ſhe ſhewed at firſt receiving it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4. She loved it ſtill, and loved it heartily, as appears by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Verſe, <hi>I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canſt not bear with them that are evil; and thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſt found them lyars: And haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my Name ſake haſt laboured, and haſt not fainted.</hi> But ſhe loved it not ſo earneſtly and heartily, as ſhe did at the beginning. She had need to quicken up her ſelf, and do the firſt works. So in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175268:11"/>
chap 3.2. fainting <hi>Sardis</hi> muſt be <hi>watchful,</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthen the things which remain, that are ready to dye;</hi> for, her works were <hi>not found perfect before God:</hi> they wede not done in that entire manner as formerly they were: So of other graces; we feel too often, and too much, how our faith, or hope, or patience, or humility, and the reſt, do meet with knocks and cracks. We make too many breaches in them. Sometimes it is too too bad. Our lives are nothing ſo profitable as they were. The care and watch is broken up in compariſon of the former diligence. The tongue is even tyed, and good ſpeech is very rare, over it was heretofore: that if we ſhould be ſtill on the loſing hand, as we are now and then, we ſhould in time prove very Bankrupts in grace, and be nothing worth toward God, and toward the ſalvation of our ſouls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The comforts of a true Chriſtian may be much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that he needs to pray with <hi>David, Reſtore unto me the joy of thy ſalvation,</hi> and, <hi>Make me to hear joy and gladneſs, that the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce, Pſal.</hi> 51.8, 12. And of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> we read an alternation of joy and ſorrow; So unto this day Gods Children find great alteration in their comforts: they have not the old feelings, they miſs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhings of the night which formerly they found; they want the joys of the Spirit in the ancient livelineſs; their aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are much decayed; the head now hangs down like a Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh which even was lifted up chearfully in looking for the day of Redemption: the voice of joy is gone from their dwellings. All is amort, and in a dump, and the man won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders what is come to him to make him ſo heavy. He hath worldly comforts as he had before; yea, and he performs the ſame duties as he did before: yet he hath not the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, either by failing in thoſe duties, or committing ſome preſumptuous ſin whereof hitherto he hath not repented, as he ſees at laſt, and ſo recovers his hold of God; but for the preſent he is very weak, as wanting <hi>the joy of the Lord which ſhould be his ſtrength, Neh.</hi> 8.10.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ask, How far may the ſtrength of a true Chriſtian be abated? <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. With Caution; the queſtion is not of the <hi>being</hi> of a Chriſtian, but of his <hi>ſtrength.</hi> He that is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175268:11"/>
once truly regenerate, is ever regenerate, and ever in the ſtate of grace: Only his grace is not alike ſtrong at all times. 2. Of them that faint, all have not their ſtrength in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or meaſure taken from them, nor the ſame Chriſtian eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of fainting. Some are grievous falls, ſome leſs; ſome are lighter fears and ſorrows, ſome heavy. Accordingly there needs more ado to recover ſome then other. On ſome we muſt have compaſſion, others we muſt ſave with fear, pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out of the fire, ſtill <hi>putting a difference</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Jude</hi> 22.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 3. It is lamentable to ſay, how far the ſtrength of a true Chriſtian may be abated.</p>
            <p>For graces, not only the exerciſe and manifeſtation of them may be ſuſpended, but even the habits themſelves much waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and things done which are quite contrary. <hi>David</hi> failed ſo far in Charity toward <hi>Uriah,</hi> that he contrived the murder of him. <hi>Peter</hi> failed ſo far in Charity toward Chriſt, that he denied and forſwore him, and that under a Curſe. So of the Drunkenneſs of <hi>Noah,</hi> the Inceſt of <hi>Lot,</hi> the rage of <hi>Aſa</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prophet, and other mad moods of good men, wherein it was ſtrange to diſcover ſo much weakneſs; and it is an horrible ſtumbling-block to the world, that the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon</hi> were ſo ſhaken; which is ſeen now and then, even at this day.</p>
            <p>For comforts: they may ſeem ſometimes to be utterly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from an holy heart, and deſpair ſet in the room; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the time of ſome ſpiritual deſertion: Oh the Lord hath forgotten to be gracious, and ſhut up his loving kindneſs in everlaſting diſpleaſure! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7, 8, 9. <hi>David</hi> laments mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully before he recovers the joy of his ſalvation. <hi>Peter</hi> weeps bitterly before he gets a good look from Chriſt again: and then he is ſhrewdly puzzled with thoſe vexing queſtions, <hi>Peter,</hi> loveſt thou me? <hi>Peter,</hi> loveſt thou me? <hi>Peter,</hi> loveſt thou me more then theſe? Good Documents for all the Lords Darlings, to be chary of their joys, and take heed of laſhing out at any time: take heed of ſecurity, take heed of wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, take heed of quenching or grieving the Spirit; It may coſt thee the ſetting on. Time may be, that neither thy ſelf nor others can afford thee comfort. Neither Reading, nor
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175268:12"/>
Praying, nor Faſting, nor all good exerciſes together can ſpeak a word of peace to thy heart; that is the work of God, and he will take his own time, both to chaſten thy diſloyalty, and to turn thy captivity, as he did for <hi>Job.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here ſome may be inquiſitive to know, what it is that thus takes away the ſtrength of a true Chriſtian. Whereto I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be, he wants his ordinary meals; and then we know a ſtrong man will grow weak quickly. It may be, he is removed from a powerful Miniſtery which ſometimes he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under: or hears not good Preaching ſo often as he was wont to do; while he heard duly and daily, he was kept in fleſh, and good heart. Or it may be, he hath caſt off his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate exerciſes of reading the Scriptures and other good Books; which ſhould both faſten and renew the things delivered in the publick Miniſtery. Or it may be, he prays not by himſelf ſo often as he uſed to do, but is a ſtranger in the Court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: the Father that ſees in ſecret, doth ſeldom ſee him in his Cloſet, in reſpect of former days. Or it may be, the exerciſe of faſting is now wholly neglected: he cannot intend it, or it is an harſh exerciſe: whereas indeed the only cauſe is, his heart is not ſo holy and ſincere as it was. Or it may be, he adventures too much, to ſtand alone in the profeſſion, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes the Aſſemblies of Saints, and ſo meets with that wo, <hi>Wo to him that is alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Too much eagerneſs upon the world ſlacks the love of heaven and heavenly things, as hath been ſaid, <hi>Amor amore impeditur;</hi> Carnal love either extinguiſheth or leſſeneth ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. Where earthlineſs is predominant, there is no love at all in ſincerity: theſe Thorns choak the ſeed of the word. Or where it creeps too much upon a good heart, the love is but weak: low Thorns do ſome miſchief to the Corn, as in <hi>Demas</hi> who for a while forſook the Apoſtle and <hi>embraced the preſent world,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. Many a good Chriſtian hath found by woful experience, that having too many Irons in the fire, or taking too many cares into his head, he hath much withered of his former greenneſs, and livelineſs in grace: the world hath proved a Step-Mother to better things, as in <hi>Martha</hi> who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175268:12"/>
was encumbred with many things. So of Ambition, itching for repute and credit in the world, till a reproof comes, <hi>Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou great things for thy ſelf? ſeek them not.</hi> So complying with evil and carnal men, till the Lord ſay, <hi>Shouldeſt thou help the ungodly?</hi> or be friends with them that hate the Lord? This is one general cauſe, why they are not ſo zealous in age, as when they were young Converts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Scandalous or preſumptuous ſins do waſte the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſtrength apace, as in thoſe holy men before rehearſed. All ſin is of a deadning and hardning nature, and ſets the Chriſtian back a little, that he is not ſo zealous as he ſhould and would be; as a Dog at his heels, keeping him from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But while it is only of infirmity, it little hinders him in his courſe; God is eaſily intreated to aſſiſt him, and continue the guidance of his Spirit: and even by ſuch rubs he gets ground daily. But when the conſcience is deeply wounded, when the light is notoriouſly reſiſted, when the heart ſmites and yet he will ruſh on, this ſhall coſt him dear; now grace goes away exceedingly, and comfort with the grace; now he is become weak as another man, and God hath ſome ſharp correction in ſtore for him, to ſet him in his right wits again. You know what evils followed <hi>David</hi> upon thoſe ſcandals. God will redeem his own glory, and the honor of holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, with the ſorrows of his evil ſervants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sometimes it is not for ſcandalous or preſumptuous ſins that the Lord forſakes his ſervants; but their unthankfulneſs for former graces, and comforts, and mercies received. They uſed them ſecurely, and gave not him the glory, as he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſerved; and therefore he leaves them for a while, and it may be, whips their own conſciences. They ſhall learn by the want, what it was to have ſo much grace and comfort, and may ſay as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.23. <hi>He weakned my ſtrength in the way: he ſhortned my days.</hi> He takes a kind of revenge for the great unkindneſs. This is the ordinary caſe of many, who keep their ways and lives ſomewhat fair, yet heavy and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. Having been unthankful, they are now left to this indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Temptation may do much. Never were the <hi>Philiſtine</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:175268:13"/>
ſo watchful to bind <hi>Samſon,</hi> and know where his great ſtrength lay, that they might deprive him of it, as the Devil is buſie to rob and ſpoil us of our ſpiritual ſtrength. For this he watcheth continually, and if he can come unobſerved, while we are ſecure and mindleſs of him, he preys upon us exceedingly. So he weakned our firſt Parents, when they were much ſtronger then we are; and <hi>David,</hi> that he numbred the people; and <hi>Peter,</hi> that he was almoſt blown away like chaff.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ordinary ſuckers that draw out much of the Life-bloud of true Chriſtians. It ſhall be our wiſdom, every one to examine his own heart and eſtate, ſo to ſee how far he is decayed in the Trade of godlineſs, and find out the true and proper cauſe of ſuch languiſhing; that ſo he may do after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward what is fit to be done, by repentance, prayer, and more care in the uſe of holy means appointed for the regaining of his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Conſider, it is miſerable, to have ones ſpiritual ſtrength ſo weakned; even as miſerable as to become poor after great wealthineſs, or ſickly after great healthineſs: A lamentable change, will nature and reaſon ſay: and grace will teach a godly man to ſay likewiſe of ſpirituals. By faith the Elders <hi>out of weakneſs were made ſtrong, and waxed valiant in fight, Heb.</hi> 11.34. And this man of ſtrong is become weak, and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in fighting the battels of the Lord. How is he decayed! Oh this woful bankruptneſs of the ſoul, whither doth it tend! and what will be the end of theſe things, unleſs the wiſer courſe be taken in time!</p>
            <p>Chriſtians, it concerns us much to lament and bewail this faintneſs, whatever it is found in any. Say not therefore, I am ſafe in the main, I cannot fall from grace, I may do well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough though I be weaker then I was. O who would miſs ſo many comforts of the Spirit, as ſuch a one muſt miſs! or walk ſo heavily as ſuch a one muſt walk! it may be, feel ſo many terrours as ſuch a one muſt feel! that there is but little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between hell and him, and he lets go that perſwaſion concerning perſeverance, and hath ſome cauſe to doubt and fear he ſhall fall quite away. I ſay, who would be in ſuch a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175268:13"/>
woful caſe? Therefore it is time to renew thy repentance, and thy covenant, and thy endeavours in footing it along in the ways of God; as now toward a Sacrament, the Lord of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers thee new ſtrength, and more occaſions to recover what is decayed ſince the laſt Sacrament: he ſpreads his Table for thee again, and hath kild his fatlings: all is prepared and ready, only be not thou unprepared and unready, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Know the only comfort is to them that take notice of their fainting, and bewail it, and would fain redreſs it. Our Text ſaith, <hi>They ſhall renew their ſtrength:</hi> Though their ſtrength do decay at times, yet it ſhall be renewed; the labour that they take againſt a Sacrament, ſhall not be loſt: therefore go in faith, and go with confidence; this is a promiſe, and ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be performed: <hi>Thou waiteſt on the Lord, therefore thou ſhalt renew thy ſtrength.</hi> Heed and believe it, and hear no accuſing voices to the contrary, either of the Devil or of thine own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing heart. Say not, I often grow weak after I have been ſtrong; therefore I fear whether ever I ſhall come to that pitch and ſtature in grace, or comfort, which ſometimes I had. Know it is our condition in this life, ſtill to ebb and flow; in heaven only we renew not our ſtrength. And divers Saints have relapſed, as we ſee in the Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. and 5. And the promiſes here are indefinite: after Relapſes ſtrength ſhall be renewed as well as in other caſes; though perhaps with more ado.</p>
            <p>Only follow on, and pray ſtill: one day thou ſhalt ſay as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 138.3. <hi>in the day when I cryed, thou anſweredſt me, and ſtrengthnedſt me with ſtrength in my ſoul.</hi> And it is greater glory to God, to preſerve ſo weak a Veſſel as thou art to his heavenly Kingdom, having ſaid, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee, my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. If we be ſtrong in the Lord and the power of his might, we are ſafe, we are ſure to do well enough. Troubled we may be, and ſhall be. The Devil, and the World, and the Fleſh will provide us troubles: but in all this Conflict we ſhall ſtand, and in the end overcome, and in overcoming is the Crown and Glory. <hi>To him that overcome, will I give ſuch and ſuch mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175268:14"/>
               <head>Now all this ſerves for Information, Conſolation, and Exhortation.</head>
               <div n="1" type="information">
                  <head>USE. I.</head>
                  <p>INformation in two things: If thoſe things ſtand for truths according to the Scripture,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Hereby is eſtabliſhed the Doctrine of Saints perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the eſtate of grace, whereinto they are brought at their converſion. When they are once regenerate, and wait on the Lord as before, they are ſure to continue in that holy and happy eſtate to the end; yea to an endleſs glory. <hi>Now and Ever;</hi> I ſpeak not any thing to magnifie our ſelves and our pure naturals, as ſome have pratled: but only to advance the grace of God in Chriſt, by whom we are able to do all things. And we ſay, It is vain whatſoever the Adverſaries object con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a mans own weakneſs, that he is apt to fall into groſs ſins, and ſhake off the grace of God, and become no ſheep, no Member of Chriſt, no Child of God, no Heir of Heaven. True, of himſelf he is apt to do ſo, and there is no other like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, but if a Chriſtian were left to himſelf, he would fall both fearfully and finally. We have an evil heart of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief to depart from the living God, and are not ſufficient of our ſelves to perſevere in the good eſtate wherein we are ſet. But what ſaith our Doctrine? the ſtrength whereby a true Chriſtian ſtandeth, is a ſtrength above that of Nature, even moſt refined. It is a borrowed ſtrength, a ſtrength deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from God, and will ſuffice him againſt all his weakneſſes, and all oppoſitions from hell and the world. It will work ſo ſtrongly in his heart, that he <hi>will not</hi> fall away, <hi>will not</hi> become a Goat when he was a Sheep, <hi>will not</hi> run out of the ſheepfold, <hi>will not</hi> of a Child of God become a Child of the Devil, nor loſe the poſſeſſion of heaven which he hath had in his eye to quicken and encourage him in his way. The fear of God is ſo put into his heart, that he neither can nor will depart from him. The gifts and calling of God are without repentance. God will never repent, that he ſo revealed himſelf to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175268:14"/>
Elect; and the Elect (by grace) ſhall never repent.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The world is hereby convinced and condemned of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing raſh and erroneous judgment upon the godly, becauſe of their falls and failings: Oh they are Hypocrites, Diſſemblers, make a ſhew of Religion, and talk much of profeſſion; but ſee how they do the contrary! But beware of Blaſphemy: It were good to huſh and be ſilent, and not condemn the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Gods Children. Know, the Chriſtian may be true, though weak: or he may be ſtrong, though weak in this or that particular; his God is able to raiſe him again, and <hi>make him ſtand, Rom.</hi> 14 4. His ſtrength ſhall be <hi>renewed,</hi> when another with his meer civilities and formalities ſhall fall, and fall without recovery. I marvel what theſe would have ſaid if they had lived in the days of <hi>David,</hi> and ſeen him ſo ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in the matter of <hi>Ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ah.</hi> Were they not Gods enemies, who blaſphemed becauſe of thoſe ſins? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. <hi>By this deed thou haſt cauſed the enemies of the Lord to blaspheme.</hi> It were time for all our Mockers and Cenſurers to repent bitterly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="information">
                  <head>USE. II.</head>
                  <p>THis ſtability of a godly mans eſtate miniſters ſingular comfort to all who upon good evidence have owned and applyed Gods mercy to their poor hearts. Their comfort is, that they ſtand not by their own ſtrength, nor ſuch a ſtrength as men of the world ſtand by, but a ſurpaſſing and excellent ſtrength which ſhall carry them bravely through the briars to a place of reſt and glory.</p>
                  <p>True ye bear about you a weak and mortal body, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, a ſinful fleſh which grieves you more then the other; and ye fear ſometimes that ye ſhall never hold out in the work of God to the end and bleſſed reward prepared for the Saints. But pluck up your hearts, and follow on carefully and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably in the uſe of means to attain the Reſurrection of the juſt. Herein ye labour and ſweat and fear, and only faint not; and ye find many diſcouragements on earth, and from hell. Well, your labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord: and know, It is not your own ſtrength that muſt do it, but his; as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175268:15"/>
the quarrel and battel is not yours, but his; thouſands ſhall fall on your right hand, and ten thouſands on the left, but you ſhall eſcape, as here it is ſaid, <hi>Even the youths ſhall faint and be weary; but they that wait on the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength.</hi> He that believes, hath the witneſs in himſelf; and he hath the fountain of life in himſelf, even the Spirit of grace as living waters, which ſhall refreſh his ſoul in every year of drought. Only believe, and thou ſhalt ſurely be eſtabliſhed. Remember, fleſh indeed is an enemy, but mortified, and God hath given us the Victory through Chriſt our Lord. More, as grace will make it; our corruption of nature ſhall further the work of God in us, by making us low in our own eyes, and driving us to the means whereby we may be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It makes us earneſt in prayer to get a ſupply from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which we cannot find upon earth. It preſerves an Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite to the word, which is the main Cordial to revive a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian heart now fainting. It ſends him often to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where he may have a good Meals meat for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his faith, and comforting of his ſoul. As likewiſe to the Society of the godly: to reading and other props which God in love hath provided to uphold him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> There is a power from hell which oppoſeth this power of grace; and may not this one time or other throw the Chriſtian quite upon his back? can Principalities and Powers do nothing, think you?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nothing, ſo as to foil or vanquiſh this ſtrong grace of God in the Saints. It is a mighty power indeed, but crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and infinitely inferiour to that Divine Power whereby a true Chriſtian ſubſiſteth. The Devil is a chained enemy, infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated, vanquiſhed; and while Gods people are w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, he will ſurely uphold them in the fight unto Victory: the God of peace will tread Satan under their feet ſhortly; and they may be <hi>perſwaded</hi> as <hi>Paul,</hi> that neither Principalities nor Powers, nor any other creatures ſhall be ever able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them from the love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 38, 39.</p>
                  <p>More comfort yet, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt that loved them they ſhall be more then Conquerors; the ſtrength which was at any time abated, ſhall be renewed again, and God will perfect the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175268:15"/>
work which he once began, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.7, 8. See ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Chriſtian is ſometimes ſtrong in faith, and gives much glory to God, and gains much chearfulneſs to himſelf, even the full aſſurance of faith: By which he reſts in the love of God with an holy ſecurity, much joy, many triumphs over hell and Satan; theſe enemies are deſpiſed as feeble <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> not able to hurt him. He got ſo much ground by the laſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and by his courſe of prayer, reading, and godly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, that he cared not if he dyed preſently, in reſpect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the ſafety of his own ſoul. But after awhile comes a cloud over his ſpirit, and he is fain to let go much of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. Yet he gets up again in little time; his ſtrength is renewed and he grows as confident as before: witneſs thoſe Viciſſitudes of joy and ſorrow in <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 30. the whole.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Patience is a ſtrong grace, ſuch as whereby a Chriſtian can <hi>poſſeſſe his ſoul</hi> in hard times, and diſtractul occaſions, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. Sometimes he is not troubled though he be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily provoked: great occaſion diſquiets him not, nor removes him from his principles; whereof <hi>Job</hi> is a notable example. Yet afterward (as in him) great breaches are made, and the ſoul even loſt by impatience. Yet, as in him, the end is with ſubmiſſion and quietneſs; <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and what end the Lord gave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The prayer of faith is omnipotent, as <hi>Luther</hi> called it; a godly man ſometimes wreſtles hard and prevailes much with God, and gets much comfort at the Throne of grace; a large and almoſt ſenſible anſwer to his prayers, a firm aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the love of God, and a part in Chriſt. Take him at ſuch a time, he is the moſt reſolute man living, ready to do or ſuffer any thing, prepared for any condition. Yet ſometimes his hands hang down as much as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and with many inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of valour and weakneſs he gets the victory over all the <hi>Amalekites</hi> in hell.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In reſpect of the ſpiritual warfare; a Chriſtian is ſtrong in the Lord and the power of his might: having put on the whole Armor of God, ſometimes he weilds it ſtoutly and wiſely, and acquits himſelf bravely for the honour of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175268:16"/>
Captain, and his own diſcharge, ſafety, glory; proſperity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigles him not, adverſity affrights him not: neither friends allure him from God and duty, nor enemies terrifie him: his watchfulneſs and jealouſie over his heart makes him invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; you would think ye ſaw ſome <hi>Alexander</hi> conquering the world, or ſome <hi>Joſhua</hi> driving down Kingdoms and Cities before him. Yet ſometimes Satan gets <hi>an advantage</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as over the Inceſtuous perſon and the other <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. The man either lay ſnorting in his great ſin, or was ready to be ſwallowed up with overmuch ſorrow: and they either neglected holy Diſcipline altogether, or elſe held him too long under that terrible cenſure of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: Yet both he and they came into right order again, chap. 7.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. And ſo other of the Lords Warriors; they forſake the field ſometimes, but ſoon get courage, and ſoon return to the field afreſh.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In reſpect of active obedience; ſometimes the life is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry preſs and ſtrict and unblameable, and profitable, the ways very fair, a very good mixture of zeal and diſcretion; good Husbandry and heavenly-mindedneſs are well matcht toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the man is even a Mirror in his place; many may take example by him, many bleſs God for him, and few can do better then he doth: And if he could keep at this ſtay, he ſhould live like an Angel upon earth. But after a while the doating fit comes, and all is off the hooks: he is either ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous with <hi>David,</hi> or ſecure with the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles.</hi> A great flaw and gap is made till all be aſhamed of him, and he weary of himſelf. A woful pickle, and damnable, but that he recovers all; as <hi>Peter,</hi> for a while a Turn-Coat, but by and by a Penitent, and at laſt a Martyr.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>The joy of the Lord is our ſtrength, Neh.</hi> 8.10. Sometimes we take much comfort in God, go about his work very chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and paſs not for ſmall rubs that lie in our way, no nor great ones: it ſufficeth that God is gracious, and we ſhall have joy and glory enough in heaven. But this bright-ſhining day ſuffers obſcurity by a cloud, when the Lord withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a little. Yet toward Evening it waxeth as bright as ever it was, as the Martyrs at the ſtake after Recantations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:175268:16"/>In every thing, with a true Chriſtian there is a recovery of loſſes to be made; it is like the dead root of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> yet bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: or as a Wheat-Corn, dead in Winter, but putting forth much ſtrength in the Summer againſt the Harveſt. And this power of renewing his ſtrength comes chiefly from God, who ſaith ſuch ſhall <hi>renew their ſtrength;</hi> and ſecondarily from themſelves, who being acted by grace will be willing all along to help themſelves: and ſo the Lord gets the honor of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing their ſtrength, and themſelves get much comfort by it.</p>
                  <p>Do ye yet want any more comfort? Then ſee a little, how this waiting on God and renewing of ſtrength may ſtand you in ſtead againſt all thoſe fears, and cares, and troubles, which at times ye are ſubject unto. No Prince when a Battel hath gone againſt him, is ſo ſure to recruit his forces, and joyn iſſue again with the enemy, as the Believer is ſure by waiting on his God to renew his ſtrength, and recover all he hath loſt: and if he fear, it is more then his good eſtate alloweth: as for inſtance.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some good ſouls are afraid they ſhall never hold on to the end: they have gone a good way in Religion, but are ſo wearyiſh in themſelves, and find the world run ſo ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that they doubt they ſhall not overcome, and then they muſt loſe their Crown. To whom I reply, This and other places aſſure us of ſufficient grounds for perſeverance in the ſtate of grace; We ſtand by the everlaſting love and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and covenant of our God. We ſtand by the grace of a Mediator, and ſo are better able to hold on then was <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency. We ſtand by the ſtrength and conduct of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Spirit of God, who will never forſake us, but abide with us for ever. We ſtand by the invincible power of faith, which through the mercy of God is able to keep us unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. We ſtand by vertue of the word, that Immortal and Incorruptible ſeed which endureth for ever. And the ſeed of God ſo abideth in us, that we ſhall not fall away, neither to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally nor finally. If ſo, what ground for theſe fears or faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some old Diſciples are much troubled with the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175268:17"/>
of old age, in mind, or body, or both; and are even wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of themſelves, and perform Religious duties but weariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: they are willing ſtill to wait upon their God, but cannot tell whether they ſhall be accepted or no, or enabled to go on to Victory. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yet ſhall ſuch be <hi>holpen with a little help, Dan.</hi> 11 34. Little in their ſenſe and apprehenſion, but not in it ſelf: it is the power of God, whereby they are kept to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and we know, that the weakneſs of God is ſtronger then men. We know alſo, that God hath enlarged his power and all his excellencies for the good of his Choſen, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 46.3, 4. <hi>Hearken unto me, O houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the remnant of the houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which are born by me from the belly, which are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed from the womb; And even to your old age I am he, and even to hoar haires I will carry you. I have made, and I will bear, and I will carry, and will deliver you.</hi> Good comfort to them whoſe underſtanding and memory fails them, with legs and ſenſes, and all that is of nature, and weather offends them whether hot or cold, and much ado they have to hold out with cheari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a little longer. Yet in their God they ſhall find a ſupply both of ſtrength and comfort, to carry them to their journies end; Only let them pray, and it ſhall be done for them. Plead as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 71 9, 12, 17, 18. <hi>Caſt me not off in the time of old age: forſake me not when my ſtrength faileth. O God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> not far from me. I will go in the ſtrength of the Lord God. O God, thou haſt taught me from my youth, and hitherto I have declared thy wondrous works. Now alſo when I am old and gray-headed, O Lord forſake me not, untill I have ſhewed thy ſtrength unto this generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thy power to every one that is to come.</hi> Where note by the way, what is the proper and chief end of deſiring long life, or the aſſiſtance of God in our way: It is that we may the better advance the glory of God, and ſerve our generation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his counſel.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Another is even tyred out with Satanical temptations and accuſations, and doubts that one time or other he ſhall fall by the hand of this helliſh enemy. Oh how black, and cunning, and inceſſant his fiery darts are! and himſelf in the mean time very weak and ſimple, and eaſie to be over-reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Can there be any hope of carrying the Victory? <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175268:17"/>
Yes, becauſe thy Captain hath ſaid, <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he ſhall fly from you:</hi> and, <hi>ye ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked one:</hi> and, <hi>the God of peace ſhall tread Satan under your feet ſhortly;</hi> and, the head of the old Serpent is ſo <hi>bruiſed</hi> by the ſeed of the Woman and his Victory, that he can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover full ſtrength againſt the remnant of her ſeed. We know too, that greater is he that is in us, then he that is in the world. We read of the weapons which we are to weild and overcome, that they are of Gods framing and appointment; the <hi>Armour of God;</hi> and, The weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God to caſt down ſtrong holds which are raiſed againſt God, and againſt our comfort; and, Not only the weapons are mighty, but we by them; <hi>Strong in the Lord and the power of his might:</hi> ſo that a ſong of triumph may be ſung by fainty Believers, <hi>Who ſhall accuſe, or condemn, or ſeparate us from the love of God in Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Certainly all the gates of hell ſhall never prevail againſt the Church of God, nor any faithful Member of it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Other Believers fear becauſe of many troubles of the family, or of the world; there are fightings without, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors within: they even faint and are weary, and ſhall be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out one time or other: what ſhall they do? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let them remember, that Chriſt hath overcome the world, and therefore though in the world they have tribulation, yet in him they ſhall have peace, and ought to be of good chear: and, <hi>Many are the afflictions of the righteous, but the Lord delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them out of all.</hi> And if deliverance be delayed, yet by the aſſiſtance of Chriſt and his Spirit the afflictions are ſweetned, and the heart ſupported, and all the ſuffering ſanctified, that in time the Chriſtian ſhall ſay, <hi>It was good for me to be afflicted, that I might learn thy ſtatutes.</hi> And remember, that when the troubles laſt longeſt, yet all the while the Chriſtian Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler is getting nearer and nearer to his Fathers houſe: ſo that, <hi>Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and his reward is with him,</hi> In the Mount it will be ſeen.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Other Believers who complain not of troubles in things of nature or the world, yet trouble themſelves much about the welfare of the Church, which they ſee endangered by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175268:18"/>
enemies; ſome undermining, others infected with errors and hereſies, and ſcattering their poiſon far and near: Oh what will become of poor <hi>Sion,</hi> which is ſo hated or defaced! many enemies, and but few real friends! <hi>Anſw.</hi> Bear up chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: it is a good ſign in thee, that thou art ſo tender of the Churches well-doing; thou haſt a promiſe, <hi>They ſhall prosper that love</hi> Sion: <hi>and all they that mourn for her, ſhall be glad and rejoyce with her, Eſa.</hi> 66.10. And as for the Church it ſelf, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, though loveſt it well, yet God loves it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and knows better how to provide for its ſafety and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt welfare, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.2. <hi>The Lord loveth the gates of</hi> Sion <hi>more then all the dwellings of</hi> Jacob. As for the enemies, ſecret or open, let the King of <hi>Sion</hi> alone to deal with them, for their converſion or confuſion, or to raiſe up friends as need ſhall require, and he ſees expedient, that the Captivity may be turned, and great gifts beſtowed for the beautifying of <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Others know not what they ſhall do, if perſecution ſhould ariſe for the Goſpels ſake: they are fainty enough un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the perſecution of the tongue, or in ſmaller tryals; and they doubt they ſhall <hi>fall utterly</hi> if fire and faggot ſhould come in uſe again. But remember here, who brought the Martyrs through the flames to give teſtimony to the truths of the Goſpel. They were fleſh and bloud as we are, and yet were ſtrengthned to paſs through the fire after Jeſus Chriſt: and they had relations and advantages to leave for the truth, as near and dear as we have, and yet by grace were enabled to part with all; yea rejoyced, that they were accounted worthy to ſuffer for the Name of Chriſt. And ye may obſerve in reading the Hiſtories of the Martyrs, how they that were very timorous for a while, yet coming in ſight of the ſtake they have waxed joyful and confident, as Mr. <hi>Glover</hi> to his friend who knew his fears, <hi>O</hi> Auſtine, <hi>He is come, he is come,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of ſtrength and comfort. Remember too, that the Lord hath continued his Church, and brought it through perſecuting times, as well as times of proſperity; yea, the Primitive Church was planted and watered, and thrived beſt in the perſecution of the firſt three hundred years. The bloud of the Martyrs proved the ſeed of the Church, to propagate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175268:18"/>
and make glorious the Kingdom of Chriſt. Therefore faint not, nor be weary for any perſecution, felt or feared.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. A Believer may ſay, <hi>Death is the King of terrors;</hi> and I fear I ſhall not dye with any patience or comfort: I know not what kind of death I ſhall dye, or where, or with what Company: it may be, by the Peſtilence, or by the Sword, or by ſome tormenting Diſeaſe, or a lingring Diſeaſe, I know not what, but I doubt I ſhall faint at the laſt; and then where is all my hope and reward? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Remember what hath been ſaid, <hi>This God is our God for ever and ever, he will be our guide even unto death, Pſal.</hi> 48.14. And not only unto death, but in dying Jeſus Chriſt will be gain unto us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. And not only Angels are <hi>ours,</hi> with other good creatures, but even death is a Friend, though he come in a Mourning Gown, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 22. And ye know how death is out-braved from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us a miſchief, chap. 15.55. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the law: But thanks be to God, who hath given us the victory through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> As for the ſad Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers and Meſſengers of death, the Lord is able, and hath promiſed to give a proportion of ſtrength and comfort; that when we faint, and the outward man decays, yet the inward man ſhall be renewed day by day; and by rich mercy ye may come to fear nothing, even when ye walk in the midſt of the valley of the ſhadow of death. And for the kind of Death, Company, Place, Time and all circumſtances, it is beſt for the Child of God to ſubmit to the will of his heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who hath ſaid, and would have us to reſt in what he hath ſaid, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> Only continue in a waiting condition as <hi>Job,</hi> all the days of thy appointed time till that great change ſhall come: thou ſhalt find it worth while, to have ſo waited.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe this waiting may be long, and there go many things to waiting; as the good ſervant who made all ready a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the coming of his Lord, I ſhall produce certain Motives as ſo many encouragements to the faithful ſervants of God, who do ſo chearfully and conſtantly attend their God in thoſe duties, and thoſe his Ordinances.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:175268:19"/>Many are the benefits of a due waiting.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This at the Text, they ſhall be enabled and bleſſed by this their waiting, <hi>To renew their strength, and hold out in the good ways of God unto glory.</hi> Though there be divers weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in themſelves, and diſcouragements in the world, yet through rich mercy they ſhall <hi>run and not be weary, walk and not faint:</hi> A ſingular priviledge, above all Apoſtates who have fallen away and come to nothing.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They have hereby a note of true grace upon them; that they are the Children and Servants of God in ſincerity, and not only in a general and common profeſſion. Our Text uſeth this <hi>Periphraſis</hi> or Deſcription of the godly, They that wait upon the Lord, ſhall do thus and thus. And it is a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Gentiles converſion, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 42.4. <hi>The Iſles ſhall wait for his law:</hi> with chap. 51.5. <hi>They ſhall wait upon me, and on thy Name ſhall they truſt:</hi> and 60.9. <hi>Surely the Iſles ſhall wait for me.</hi> It is an ordinary Inquiry among tender ſpirits, Whether am I indeed converted and brought home unto God or no? The ſolution may hence be taken, If ye wait on the Lord in the way and manner before deſcribed, ye are indeed convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and need not trouble your ſelves any more.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Another benefit is, that theſe Waiters ſhall not in any thing be utterly diſappointed, ſo as to be aſhamed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded; but one way or other ſhall receive ſatisfaction at the hands of God according to their expectation: Either he will give them the thing deſired, or what ſhall be better, either here or hereafter, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.23. <hi>They ſhall not be aſhamed that wait for me.</hi> They that wait upon great men in the world, do find infinite diſappointments, ſhame, ſorrow, and ſometimes heart-breaking: but ſo ſhall not they that wait on the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Such ſhall have their Prayers heard, and their Petitions granted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.1. <hi>I waited patiently for the Lord, and he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined unto me, and heard my cry.</hi> This waiting makes that a Chriſtian paſſeth over a delay, and conſtrueth it not for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial; and holds up his head to the time wherein God will be ſeen for him. The like of the prayers that other Believers make in our behalf: <hi>wait, and we ſhall reap the benefit of them,</hi> Pſal. 25.3. <hi>Let none that wait on thee, be aſhamed.</hi> A very
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175268:19"/>
comfortable matter in this life of neceſſities urging us on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Theſe Waiters have many ſecrets revealed to them, and many experiments of the love of God, which others ſhall not have: they are ſtill in the way of preferment, and ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taily have it one time or other, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.11. <hi>The poor of the flock that waited upon me, knew that it was the word of the Lord. The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him. He will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt himſelf to the faithful obſervers of his will,</hi> and not to others. It is an excellent poſture, <hi>to abide with Chriſt in temptation. To be faithful to the death,</hi> is the ready way to the Crown of Life.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It will be great joy on the Death-bed, ſo to have waited on the Lord; as dying <hi>Jacob</hi> found, who amidſt the bleſſing of his Children brake out into this Extaſie, <hi>I have waited for thy ſalvation O Lord, Gen.</hi> 49.18. And when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſentence of death, he could ſay in faith, <hi>Remember how I have walked before thee in uprightneſs of my heart.</hi> And ſo may other Believers ſay in all oppoſitions of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.21. <hi>Let integrity and uprightneſs preſerve me, for I wait on thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Unſpeakable happineſs is prepated for theſe our Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 64.4. <hi>From the beginning of the world men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye ſeen O God, beſide thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him.</hi> Now at laſt it appears how bleſſed they are, and what it is to have the Lord waiting to do them good. Now they have the reward of all their patience and conſtancy. Now they ſee they took the wiſer and ſafer courſe. Evil men had the ſtart of them in the world, and triumphed over them: even thoſe that <hi>wait not for the counſel of God, Pſal.</hi> 106.13. <hi>nor the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God,</hi> 2 King. 6.33. <hi>Should I wait for the Lord any longer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They deſpiſed the godly for being ſo ſtrict, and mopiſh, and obſervant, waiting upon God at an inch. They caſt out their name as evil, and watched to do them a miſchief; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being in the mean time the only men of note. But now when the parting place comes, and the day of diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of rewards appeareth; now it appears how good it was to wait upon the Lord at every turn, and with conſtancy. The conſcionable hearing, and repeating, and obeying of good
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175268:20"/>
Sermons, the reverent frequenting of the Lords Table, the joyful and careful ſpending of Sabbaths, the diligent main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and holding up of holy Diſcipline in the Family, all the good words that have been ſpoken, all the good actions that have been done, ſhall now be rewarded liberally and plentifully. And now they ſhall wait upon the Lord in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner then ever in this life, only to behold and partake of his glory, for their full happineſs and contentment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="information">
                  <head>USE. III.</head>
                  <p>AFter all thoſe comforts that accrew by waiting on God, and ſo renewing our ſtrength for haſtning toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it behoves us to think on ſome duties to be performed; that ſo we may be anſwerable to the great loving kindneſſe of our God, who firſt promiſed, and now hath performed this mercy and truth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The godly ſhould take notice of this mighty ſtrength whereby they ſtand, and acknowledge it, ſo to become truly and unfainedly thankful: not droop in themſelves, but be hearty and cheary; nor diſgrace their holy profeſſion to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if it were a profeſſion all made of dumps and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, nor (which is the ſpecial thing) to defraud, and deprive God of his due honour. It becomes the juſt to be thankful. Praiſe is comely for the upright. Therefore go to thy houſe, and tell what great things the Lord hath done for thee: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that mighty power whereby thou ſtandeſt; let it appear, both in the chearfulneſs and uprightneſs of thy life. It is a ſingular malice of the Devil, and alſo weakneſs in corrupt nature, not to acknowledge the work of God in the ſoul, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more miſchief then we are aware. Therefore herein watch, both thine own weakneſs and the Devils wickedneſs. As it is dangerous to preſume of a ſtrong faith and grace, where none is; ſo it is a ſullen and unthankful ſheepiſhneſs not to take notice of it where it is. God loſeth his glory, and the Chriſtian his portion and comfort.</p>
                  <p>And it is expedient for us to know where our ſtrength li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that ſo we may walk in it for the end it was given us; as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175268:20"/>
is ſaid of the Primitive Churches, <hi>That walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, they were multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Act 9.</p>
                  <p>And, Never ſhall the Chriſtian demean himſelf more bravely and generouſly, then when he conſiders and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers he hath received a power whereby he can over match all the adverſary powers, both of hell and earth: They are all very weaklings in compariſon of him, and he can ſafely bid defiance to them all; <hi>Who ſhall accuſe, or condemn, or ſeparate us from the love of God in Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> yet ſtill he will be humble and modeſt, becauſe he knows it is a borrowed ſtrength. <hi>We are ſtrong in the Lord, and the power of his might.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. This may be an encouragement to the godly, to go on with their pains and diligence in holy exerciſes, foraſmuch as they know they ſhall get ſtrength by them, and ſuch ſtrength as infinitely ſurmounts all ſtrength of nature, both Humane and Angelical. They ſeem weak Ordinances, and not able to produce any worthy effects, <hi>viz.</hi> Reading Hearing, Praying, Faſting, Talking together. Worldly-wiſe men deride ſuch courſes, and many think there is no good to be got by them: elſe why do they neglect them as they do? But indeed they are mighty through God to the caſting down of high holds, and the ſetting up of high fortreſſes of grace and comfort in ſtead thereof. There ſhall be Bread to the Sower, and good ſucceſs to him that laboureth. Other labour is not ſo ſure to ſpeed and take effect, even when they have run to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and round about the world. Therefore labour on as thou haſt begun, and digeſt all the pains that are to be taken in fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for heaven: as for example,</p>
                  <p>Follow on ſtill to enjoy the Preaching of the Word, though Painful, Hateful, Chargeable. It is the power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to every one that believeth. It is the ſavour of life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life, and uſeful divers ways, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Then go to the Prophets, though an Husband ſay there is no cauſe, or a Wife, or a Father, or Mother, or Friend, or Maſter.</p>
                  <p>Faſt ſtill in a Religious manner: be not wearied with the uncouthneſs of the exerciſe; it is powerful to do mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels: ſturdy Devils have been caſt out by Faſting and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175268:21"/>
Prayer, and ſo may ſtout corruptions which ſeem untameable.</p>
                  <p>So for the Sacrament: it is an effectal Ordinance of God, to Seal up his love to the ſoul more throughly, to ſtrengthen faith, to quicken an holy heart, to enable us unto holy duties, and holy converſation, as it were with a new addition of ſtrength. It is another Seal of the Righteouſneſs of faith. We may be well aſſured and cheared by it. Therefore take pains more then ordinary, be not ſo formal and ſlight in preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, examine thy eſtate more fully and particularly, lament thy imperfections more deeply, diſcern the Lords body more carefully and reverently, provide better then ever heretofore, to be a welcome Gueſt at the Lords Table.</p>
                  <p>It is true: to do this as it ought to be done, will require ſome time, and ſome retiredneſs, and ſome thought-taking, with ſorrows and fears, and it may be, ſome anguiſh of mind. But be contented for all that; the Harveſt will pay for all the labour of the Seed-time; thou ſhalt ſee in little time, how good it was for thee to be ſo reverent and devoutly affected; when Gods face ſhall ſhine upon thee more then before, and thy Conſcience more cheared and cleared, and thy weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes helped, and thy life in all points rectified, thou ſhalt bleſs the time that ever thou ſetteſt to do the work of the Lord ſo exactly and ſubſtantially.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There be three duties that lie couched in the Similitude here uſed, whereby the perpetuity of the Saints in grace is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: <hi>They ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, aad they ſhall walk and not faint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is reported of the Eagle, that ſhe is very long-lived: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>quaſi</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as if the Eagle had always a year to live; being old, ſhe becomes young again, and not once, but often: and when ſhe dyes, it is rather that ſhe cannot eat for the length and crookedneſs of her Beak, then for want of vigor and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. This her Beak a long time ſhe caſteth (ſay <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) as other creatures do their horns, and then ſhe can feed afreſh, and be as lively as ever. So it is a fit Similitude to expreſs the vivacity of Believers whoſe life Chriſt is; they ſhall renew their ſtrength by waiting on the Lord as before, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 103.8. <hi>Who ſatisfieth thy mouth with good things, ſo that thy youth is renewed as the Eagles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:175268:21"/>But to follow that Similitude which is more expreſs in the Text, <hi>Of mounting up with wings as Eagles:</hi> It is but a fable of <hi>Zaadias</hi> the Jew, that every tenth year the Eagle flies to the ſphear of the Sun, and there burns off her feathers with the heat of the Sun-beams, and ſo grows young again for an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years. This is confeſt on all hands, that the Eagle flies higher then any other Bird: and thence the Proverb is riſen, <hi>Aquila in nubibus,</hi> ſpoken of one that ſoars aloft in remote and abſtruſe matters, which the common ſort of men can never reach into. And here applyed to Believers, may note their heavenly-mindedneſs: they ſet their affections on things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and not on things which are upon earth. It notes alſo their agility and chearfulneſs in fulfilling their courſe: though ſin as a weight preſs them down, yet they force up their hearts again, and ſtill affect the way to heaven as the only way they can take for happineſs.</p>
                  <p>Then for the other words, <hi>They ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint:</hi> As in the word of <hi>running</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) is noted fervor and alacrity of ſpirit, ſo in the word of <hi>walking</hi> the Prophet ſets forth the continuance of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; So that in this Similitude we have three things which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to the godly, partly as duties, partly as priviledges; Heavenly-mindedneſs, Chearfulneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Conſtancy in their holy courſe. We will ſpeak of them ſeverally, that the Uſes may be more plain and diſtinct.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctr.</hi> 1. It is the nature of true Believers to lift up their hearts toward ſpiritual and heavenly things, and ſo they muſt remember to do as of duty, <hi>Col</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>If ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God: ſet your affections on things above, and not on things on the earth.</hi> And the Pſalmiſt calls them a <hi>brood of Travellers, in ſeeking the face of God,</hi> Pſal. 24.6.</p>
                  <p>For why? they are born of an heavenly Principle, which is the Spirit of God: and their treaſure (as they profeſs) is in heaven; therefore there alſo muſt their hearts be. And in the world they find a great deal of ſin, oppoſition to good, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and hindrance from better things, vanity and vexation of ſpirit; no contentment in any thing, no certainty; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175268:22"/>
why ſhould they ſtay below? why ſhould they not mount upward, where they are ſure to be ſafe, and ſatisfied, and that for ever and ever? the Bird is ſafeſt when ſhe keeps higheſt: on earth there are ſnares, and enemies everywhere, and that continually.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe.</hi> To reprove earthly-minded people, who are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet upon things below; Profits, Lands, Houſes, Honors, Eaſie living, Voluptuouſneſs; ſo that they would care for no other heaven, if they might always live where they do. They plainly ſhew themſelves to be but Crows and Buzzards, who never get higher then the loweſt Region: therefore one day they are likely to come to a fearful end, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>They mind earthly things, and their end is deſtruction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It muſt alſo check and condemn the earthly-mindedneſs of the godly themſelves, who <hi>mount</hi> not up as they ought to do, but too much reſt in theſe vanities below; as if of <hi>Eagles</hi> they would turn ſome vile and baſe Birds, whom any Carrion will content well enough.</p>
                  <p>It is too lamentable to ſee, how ſome good men are rivet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the earth and inordinately ſeek after profit, till grace wither, and they begin to fall into a Conſumption in reſpect of their ſouls. The time, and thoughts, and cares, and affections, which ſhould be bent and ſpent upon heaven and the things thereof, are now turned for earth and earthly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages. The heart is ſtraightned and almoſt ſhut up for any charges toward good uſes. All is for the Wife and Children, and their own contentment according to the perverſe humor which is grown in the ſoul.</p>
                  <p>Others are for their Honors and Preferments, as if they would have a <hi>Jeremy</hi> come and reprove them in thoſe words to <hi>Baruch, Seekeſt thou great things to thy ſelf?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others too much hang upon evil and ungodly men, or too much ſeek to keep in with the wicked multitude; as if they meant no longer to be the Servants of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. <hi>If I go about to pleaſe men, I am not the Servant of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others are held from good duties through fear of men, and kept in a luke-warm indifferency, as if with <hi>Laodicea</hi> they thought good to be ſpewed out of the mouth of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:175268:22"/>For diſguiſed faſhions, there is no talk now, but they muſt be tolerated, and may be uſed: the Preachers were as good hold their peace, as ſeek to take off theſe ſuperfluities from their heads and ſhoulders: they ſhall but get ill-will, for ſpeaking againſt theſe faſhions. And ſo of Marriages: Sons of God now-a-days marry the Daughters of men, and contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and there is no remorſe for it, no ſin in it; all is well, if there be State and Portion enough, with other the like vanities.</p>
                  <p>In many things we ſee great embaſement come upon the profeſſed ſervants of God, and ſuch as we hope do ſerve him in truth: To whom I may ſay as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, admiring the fine ſtones and buildings of the Temple, <hi>Are theſe the things that ye look upon?</hi> are theſe the contentful Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of renewed ſouls? what, is your underſtanding enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and your judgment rectified, and yet ſo dote upon ſuch trifles as theſe are? Why, what need <hi>wings</hi> to mount up after theſe things? theſe are the common prey of every unclean and baſe-conditioned Bird that never flies aloft: theſe are for <hi>Owls,</hi> and not for <hi>Eagles;</hi> you ſhall leave theſe for <hi>men of this world, who have their portion in this life,</hi> Pſal. 17.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Where the Carkaſe is, thither will the Eagles be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. He ſpake it of himſelf, and of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to judgment: Wherever he would appear to judge the world, thither the godly would reſort, and come unto him. Conſider, and gather up thy affections for heaven, and make them as many, as frequent, as earneſt as ever they were. Chriſt is that ſacred Carkaſe, whereon thy ſoul muſt feed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal life: and if thou be an <hi>Eagle</hi> indeed, thou wilt ſcent him ſtrongly afar off, and long for him, and haſten after him as faſt as thou canſt. Well, do; ſo here is now a Sacrament at hand and thereby an occaſion to renew thy love of Chriſt, and of the things that pertain to his Kingdom. Now ſtir up thy ſelf to thy ancient affections and actions, renew thy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, ſoar aloft as thou waſt wont to do; let us ſee thee after this Sacrament more heavenly-minded then thou haſt been of late days; let thy ſpeeches and courſes ſpeak louder that thou art for heaven in good ſadneſs as we ſay;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175268:23"/>
ſay more, do more, give more, ſpend more, which may help thee in that journey.</p>
                  <p>The Jews upon their eating the Paſſover muſt preſently walk out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and thereunto in eating muſt have a ſtaff in their hand. Let the Moral be thus: this heavenly Banquet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an heavenly Appetite, affection, converſation after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Get out of the <hi>Egypt</hi> of this world as faſt as thou canſt. He is an holy and happy Chriſtian, who takes every occaſion to unfaſten his heart from the world; earthly in it ſelf, even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace received, and muſt be skrewed up by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, upon every advantage that it may take. So, as he hath leſs earthly joy, he ſhall have more of the heavenly. The ſweet peace with God and his own Conſcience will infinitely countervail the want of all other peace and comfort whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. And thrice happy are thoſe ſouls, who by a right eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the worth of heavenly things, and by a godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie over their own hearts do keep their thoughts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections above, ſtill looking downward with an holy diſdain and wearineſs. It is an high pitch of great grace, for the heart to ſay, and the life make it good, <hi>Vanity of vanities, vanity of vanities, all is vanity and vexation of spirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctr.</hi> 2. It is the nature and duty of Chriſtians truly fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, to be chearful and lively in their holy courſe: as the <hi>Eagles</hi> are nimble and full of ſpirits to mount upward, ſo are and muſt Believers be; the Lord loves a chearful giver, and that is reaſon enough, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>They muſt run and walk:</hi> run, and <hi>not be weary;</hi> walk, and <hi>not faint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe.</hi> If they be not thus chearful, it is a fault, and muſt be amended. It is becauſe they wait not on the Lord ſo duly and carefully as they ought to do. The promiſe is not performed, becauſe the condition is not obſerved. Many Chriſtians may wonder at themſelves, what is come to them, that they are ſo heavy, ſo unweildy, ſo timerous, ſo backward in the way of godlineſs. Their ſpirits are even gone: they have not the heavenly Meditations that ſometime they had: they delight not in the preſence of God, to come before him in prayer, as ſometime they did: Accordingly they have but cold comfort, and poor anſwer returned after their prayer. They make not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175268:23"/>
good motions, nor put in a good word, as heretofore. Carnal fear and modeſty have ſeiſed upon them. Some one way, and ſome another, are mightily come behind themſelves, and that meaſure of livelineſs which ſometime was in them. Hereupon they are troubled about their Eſtate, or have juſt cauſe to be troubled.</p>
                  <p>Well, let this be a watch-word to them, to become as chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as ever. Say O Chriſtian, in every ſuch caſe, as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Why art thou ſo caſt down, O my ſoul? and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me?</hi> what is the matter, that I am ſo unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Stir up the gift that is in thee: ariſe and ſhake thy ſelf as <hi>Samſon</hi> when he was bound with chains or cords; repent and do the <hi>firſt works:</hi> repent and entertain the <hi>firſt Love again: Return O Shulam te, return, return.</hi> Thou haſt the Spirit of God in thee, quench him not, ſet him on work as lively as ever: Pray, and it ſhall be done. Or, if that will not ſerve the turn, faſt away this dull and melancholy Devil which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth thee, as is ſaid, This kind goeth not out but by faſting and prayer. Renew thy Covenant and Vows, do ſomething more then ordinary; that is the way to be as lively as ever thou waſt.</p>
                  <p>Conſider the occaſion which the Lord now offers unto thee. Upon a good Banquet we uſe to be more lively then we were, and to gather up our ſpirits which were almoſt ſpent and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. No ſuch Banquet as the Lord makes for his ſervants, the fleſh of his Son which is meat indeed, and the blood of his Son which is drink indeed. Theſe are the <hi>fat things,</hi> the <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Milk</hi> of the Goſpel, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. How can a Chriſtian go right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this Banquet, and not be the better for it? How is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible? Well, remember what that is, <hi>to go rightly,</hi> and do it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: it is often ſhewed in our miniſtery, and you called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; none can ſay he knows not. Then ſettle to do it. He that loves grace indeed, and the comforts of grace, let him ſtrive to be lively, and get as much of it as he can.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctr.</hi> 3. It is the nature and duty of good Chriſtians to be conſtant in their good courſes to the end: not to be <hi>weary</hi> when they run, nor <hi>faint</hi> when they walk. The duty is in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Be thou faithful unto the death.</hi> The priviledge is in this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175268:24"/>
place. They are born of incorruptible ſeed, led by an holy Spirit that abides with them for ever, embraced with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting love and Covenant, ſtrengthned by a mighty faith which overcomes the world, and quencheth the fiery darts of the Devil. And this of the Text ſtands by way of promiſe, <hi>They ſhall</hi> mount up, <hi>They ſhall</hi> run and not be weary, <hi>They ſhall</hi> walk and not faint. Now all the promiſes of God in Chriſt are <hi>Yea and Amen.</hi> The Oath and Promiſe of God are <hi>two im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable things,</hi> wherein it is impoſſible he ſhould be deceived, or deceive.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> They are weary oftentimes, and <hi>faint</hi> in their courſe: afflictions diſhearten and unſettle them, corruption of nature even foils them; Satan gets within them. <hi>Anſw.</hi> At the worſt they fall not either totally or finally: nor are ever ſo weary or faint, but their ſtrength is renewed again; and they may ſay as the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9, 16. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, yet not diſtreſſed; we are perplexed, but not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair; perſecuted, but not forſaken; caſt down, but not deſtroyed. We faint not, but though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe.</hi> Let all that wait on the Lord with their hearts, both rejoyce in their priviledge, and look well to their duty.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Rejoyce in your priviledge. Your endeavours in holy ways ſhall be Crowned with perſeverance, and your perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with glory. Your deſires ſhall be anſwered and ſatisfied to the full. When many fall, you ſhall ſtand. And in the day when you are ſhrewdly ſhaken, yet ſtill you ſhall ſtand; or if you fall, you ſhall ſurely riſe again. True, you muſt fear in reſpect of your ſelves and your own unſtedfaſtneſs: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God you have no cauſe at all to fear or be diſmayed. Through the mercy and grace of your God who hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you are as ſure one day to be in heaven, as now you are upon earth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Look to your duty, that is, to <hi>keep your ſelves in the love of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> adviſeth. <hi>Be not high-minded, but fear:</hi> and, <hi>Let him that ſtandeth, take heed left he fall.</hi> Holy joy never breeds ſecurity, nor a neglect of the means, as carnal and preſumptuous us uſeth to do.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:175268:24"/>And, not only work out your ſalvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, to ſhun a total and final Apoſtaſie, but take heed of partial and temporary backſlidings: admit as few interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the way of well-doing, as poſſibly you can: ſtill ſhake up your ſelves out of every wearineſs, and every fainting. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the preparative, though not to everlaſting deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet temporary chaſtiſement, eſpecially in the ſoul, by the abſence of Chriſt, who withdraws a while when ſecurity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. and 5. Ever fear to come any whit near that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal concluſion of hypocrites, who one time or other fall away, and ſhew they were never the men and women that they would be taken to be; not <hi>of us,</hi> though among us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. And of ſuch the Lord ſaith, <hi>If any man draw back, my ſoul hath no pleaſure in him:</hi> and they draw back <hi>to perdition, Heb.</hi> 10.39.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="information">
                  <head>USE. IV.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Concluſion.</head>
                  <p>ALL this ſo being, may encourage all to a godly life, and to receive the grace of God when it is offered to them, as that which will ſet them in ſuch a bleſſed and permanent condition, above all the excellency nature is any way able to reach or attain. Alaſs man, what art thou by nature? in the greateſt of thy ſtrength thou art but a fainting, dying man: In thy youth, the flower of thine age, thou mayeſt be ſoon cropt and defaced, and then without grace in thy heart thou goeſt to hell as ſurely as <hi>Belzebub.</hi> What is the ſtrength of legs, or beauty, or nimbleneſs, or healthineſs, or any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral endowments? pretty things in their kind, and ſuch as whereof a good uſe may be made: but in reſpect of Gods favor and heaven, very trifles. If ſo, then much more honor, riches, pleaſures, eaſe, dainty diet, and the like: theſe ſome call the gifts of fortune, and Scripture ſaith, they take them wings, <hi>and profit not them that have been exerciſed in them, Heb.</hi> 13.9. Wiſdom would, that a man look beyond all theſe to the better and enduring ſubſtance. It is good that the heart be <hi>eſtabliſhed with grace, and not with meats.</hi> He that is born anew unto God,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175268:25"/>
ſhall alſo be ſtrong in God. Though his beginning be but ſmall and weak, yet his latter end ſhall increaſe exceedingly. Others of ſtrong ſhall become weak, he of weak ſhall become ſtrong. Let us hear the end of all: <hi>All fleſh is graſs, and the glory of man as the flower of the field: the graſs withereth, and the flower fadeth away; but the word of the Lord endureth for ever, and this is the word which by the Gospel we preach unto you,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.24, 25.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
